Okay, so in this first lecture,
好的，在这第一讲里，
I want to ask a question.
我想提一个问题。
The question is,
问题是，
why did humanity transition
为什么人类从狩猎采集社会转向农业？
from hunter -gatherer society to agriculture?
好的？在传统范式里，一个范式。
Okay? And in the traditional paradigm, a paradigm.
Paradigm is a very
范式是一个很精细的英文词，
sophisticated English word, and
它的全部意思是故事或模型或理解。
all it means is story or model or understanding.
all it means is story ormodel or understanding.
Okay? So in a traditional story paradigm,
好的？在传统的故事范式里，
we transitioned because
我们转变是因为
we're first hunter -gatherers
我们是最早的狩猎采集者
and we lived in groups of about 20 to 50 people
我们住在大约20到50人的小团体里
and we roamed the land looking for food.
我们在陆地上四处寻找食物
It was uncertain.
那时还不确定
It was unstable. And then suddenly there was a Revolution.
它不稳定。随后突然出现了一场革命。
we discover farming and
我们发现了耕作，且
farming provided a stable source of food
耕作提供了稳定的食物来源
that we could control okay the word
那我们可以掌控的词是“驯化”
we use is domestication okay domestication just means
驯化只是意味着
that we bring it under our control
我们把它纳入我们的掌控之中
and because
因为
of farming we can now create
由于耕作我们现在可以创造
more food than we need the word we use for this is surplus
多于需求的食物，称之为剩余
and because
因而
there's a surplus people now could do things besides farming
由于有剩余，人民现在可以做除耕作之外的事
so for example we could have leaders
例如，我们可以有领袖
which
哪一
creates the idea of politics right we could also have priests
创建政治概念，随后我们也能有祭司
which
introduces the idea of religion we can have creative people right
引入宗教概念，我们可以有创造性的人才
which then gives us arts and
随后产生艺术与…
slowly over time these villages grew into cities
随着时间推移，这些村落发展成城镇
and because
并且
there was a lot of people in our surplus we could now have literature
因为我们有了剩余，人数多了，我们就能有文学
reading and writing so
阅读与书写
we can now store knowledge and then pass it from generation to generation
我们现在可以存储知识，并将其代代相传
and across cultures okay we're gonna have science
并且跨文化传递，随后便有了科学
and technology and
以及技术
slowly over the course of this process we create modernity,
在这一过程的推进中，慢慢地我们创造了现代性，
okay? Which is the world that we live in today.
好吧？这就是我们今天所处的世界。
So the pivotal step
于是关键一步是……
towards modernity was this transition into agriculture.
向现代性的过渡是这一次向农业的转变。
And this is traditionally what we believed about the world.
这正是我们传统上对世界的理解。
Unfortunately, there's no evidence for this, okay?
不幸的是，这点没有证据，好的？
And in fact, the more evidence we collect,
而且，收集的证据越多，我们越发现这点不对。
the more we realize this is not true.
事实上，】
In fact,
what we now know is it was
我们现在知道的是，它是……
actually pretty stupid to transition
实际上从狩猎采集转向农耕是相当愚蠢的……
from hunter -gatherer into farming, okay?
……好吧？
For a variety of reasons.
因为多种原因。
The first reason is that when
第一个原因是，当……
you're a hunter -gatherer, it's actually a pretty easy life.
当你是狩猎采集者时，生活其实相当轻松。
Okay? Because there's food everywhere, okay?
好的？因为到处处都有食物，好吗？
When you're a farmer, it's a hard life because you have to grow that food.
当你是农夫时，生活很辛苦，因为你得种那食物。
So maybe as a hunter -gatherer, you're working maybe an hour a day,
所以说，狩猎采集者一天大约工作一小时。
but as a farmer, you were working six, seven hours a day.
但当你是农夫时，你一天大约工作六七个小时。
It was very hard to grow that food.
种那食物非常辛苦。
So in the book Sapiens,
于是《万物生长》一书里说，
the Israeli
以色列人
historian named Yoel Harari, he's very famous,
以色列人史学家约埃尔·哈拉里，他很有名气，
Sapiens is also a very famous book, there's a very famous sentence, okay?
《万物生长》也是一本很有名气的书，有一句很有名气的话，
The sentence is like this, we did not
句子是这样：我们没有驯化小麦。
domesticate wheat.
小麦驯化了我们。
Wheat domesticated us, okay?
好吧？
So we thought that we made wheat, okay,
于是我们认为我们把小麦——我们的食物——变成了奴隶。
the food wheat, into our slave.
但实际上，…
But in reality,
wheat made us its slave.
小麦让我们成为它的奴隶。
And the reasoning for this is this.
原因就是这样。
Okay? Out in nature, if you're wheat and you want to survive,
自然界里，如果你是小麦，想要存活，
you have to make yourself attractive to other people and to animals, okay?
你得让自己对别人和动物都有吸引力，行吗？
So you have to be tasty and you have to be easy to find.
所以你得好吃又容易被发现。
You have to do a lot of work.
你得做很多工作。
But when you're on a farm and you're wheat,
但当你在农场里，像小麦一样时，你只需躺下不动，让人类来做所有工作。
you can just lay back, do nothing, and make humans do all the work.
好了？于是对人类来说是个好交易。
Okay? So it was a bad deal for humans
好的？于是对人类来说是个好交易。
and a very good deal for wheat, okay?
并且对小麦来说是个非常好的交易，行吗？
So that's the first problem. You actually do more work on the farm than you do as a hunter -gatherer.
于是这就是第一个问题。你在农场里做的工作比狩猎采集时多。
Which means that now you have to have more children, right?
这意味着你现在需要多生孩子，对吧？
You need to have labor to do all that work, which
你需要劳动力来完成所有工作，这
creates a problem of overpopulation.
导致人口过剩问题。
Which means that you are using too much land and
这意味着你使用了过多的土地，
then eventually the land becomes dead, okay?
于是土地最终变成了荒地，行吗？
Or not arable anymore.
或者不再可耕种。
So it's the first problem. Second problem is that we're able to
于是第一个问题。第二个问题是我们能做到
dig up the skeletons of hunter -gatherers and farmers.
挖掘狩猎采集者和农民的骨骼
And what we see is that
我们看到的是
hunter -gatherers are a lot taller than farmers.
狩猎采集者比农民高很多
Why? Protein, right?
为什么？蛋白？
Food. As a hunter -gatherer, you have access to meat.
食物。作为狩猎采集者，你能吃到肉。
You have access to fruits and nuts and vegetables, okay?
你能吃到水果、坚果和蔬菜，行吗？
Your diet is varied and very nutritious.
你的饮食多样且非常有营养。
But as a farmer, you have to have a lot of food.
但作为农夫，你必须有大量食物。
You have to have a lot of food. You have to have a lot of nature. You have to have nature. You have to have nature. And as a farmer, you're eating only what you grow,
你必须有大量食物。你必须有大量自然。你必须有自然。你必须有自然。作为农夫，你只吃自己种的东西。
which is mainly wheat and some vegetables, okay?
主要是小麦和一些蔬菜，行吗？
So you're not getting that much nutrition.
所以你获得的营养不多。
And the third problem is that as a farmer,
第三个问题是，作为农夫，
you are much more likely to die early than if you're a hunter -gatherer.
你比狩猎采集者更容易早逝。
Why? Have you guys been to a farm?
为什么？你们去过农场吗？
What's the problem on a farm?
农场有什么问题？
Exactly. Thank you. pigs, right?
好的。谢谢。猪，对吧？
Animals, they're everywhere.
动物，它们无处不在。
Plus, where do you put the garbage?
另外，垃圾放在哪里？
Where do you go to the restroom, right?
你去洗手间的路怎么走？对吧？
So because people are together in a very unclean place,
所以因为人们聚集在一个非常不干净的地方，
it's much more likely to contract disease and then die.
更可能感染疾病然后死亡。
Okay? So for these three reasons,
好的？所以这三点原因，转向农耕的过程，
the transition from hunter -gatherer
猎人采集者到农耕的转变
to farming makes no sense.
农耕毫无意义。
And even today,
即使到今天，
we are not able to explain
我们无法向你解释这次转变的原因。
to you why this transition happened.
Okay? We don't know why we did this. So
好的？我们不知道为什么会这么做。所以
the only thing we can do is construct theories as to why this might have happened.
唯一能做的就是构造理论来解释可能发生的原因。
So even though we can't go in the past and
于是即使我们无法回到过去去观察我们为何这么做，
look at why we did this,
我们仍然可以做研究并收集证据，然后构造理论来解释这件事。
we can do some research and collect evidence
我们可以做研究并收集证据
and then create theories as to why this happened.
然后构造理论来解释这件事。
Okay? So
好的？所以
there are four different disciplines from which we can collect evidence.
我们可以从四个不同的学科收集证据。
The first discipline is called archaeology.
第一个学科叫做考古学。
Archaeology is just the study of the past.
考古学就是研究过去的学科。
So basically, you go and you dig stuff up and you see what you can find. Okay?
基本上就是去挖掘东西，看看能挖到什么。好吗？
Maybe you can dig up someone's house or you can dig up someone's skeleton or someone's clothing.
也许你能挖出某人的房屋，或挖出某人的骨骸，或挖出某人的衣物。
Okay? And from that,
好的？从中你能推断过去发生的事。
you're able to figure out what happened in the past. And so
于是，三条考古证据是……
three pieces of evidence from archaeology we
will look at today are Gobekli Tepe, Jericho,
今天我们要看的地方是戈贝克利塔佩、耶利哥和卡塔尔霍耶克。
and Katahaljóek.
好的？这些地方是……
Okay? And these are places that
Okay? And theseare places that
we've actually dug up and we know what life is like in these three places.
我们已经挖掘出来并且知道这三地的生活状况。
So that's archaeology.
这就是考古学。
Second discipline we can look at is anthropology.
第二个我们可以研究的学科是人类学。
And anthropology is the study of other cultures.
人类学是研究其他文化的学科。
So in other words, there are places still on this planet
换句话说，地球上还有一些地方，那里的人们仍然以狩猎采集的方式生活。
where people live a hunter -gatherer lifestyle.
Maybe in the Amazon, maybe in Australia,
也许在亚马逊，也许在澳洲，
maybe in Africa. Okay? And so we're able to go and
也许在非洲。好了？于是我们可以去
study these people to understand why,
研究这些人，了解原因
how originally we thought
我们最初的想法
and why we might have transitioned into farming.
以及我们为何可能转向农耕
Okay? So anthropology. The third field
好了？所以是人类学。第三个领域
that we can look at is psychology or neuroscience.
我们可以研究的第三个领域是心理学或神经科学。
Basically how the brain works.
基本上就是大脑的工作原理。
How do we feel? What motivates us?
我们是怎样感受？是什么驱动我们？
Why do we behave the way we behave?
我们为什么会这样表现？
Okay? So that's a third field we can look at.
好了？这就是我们可以研究的第三个领域。
The last field we can look at is primatology.
我们可以研究的最后一个领域是灵长类学。
The study of primates.
灵长类的研究。
Okay? Or monkeys. Because guess what guys?
好了？或者猴子。因为猜猜看谁？
We're monkeys. We're primates.
我们是猴子。我们是灵长类。
995 007 percent of our DNA are monkey DNA.
95.00% 的 DNA 是猴子DNA。
So we can look at certain groups of monkeys to understand how they behave.
我们可以研究某些猴子群体来了解它们的行为。
And there are three types of primates that we look at very closely.
我们非常仔细地研究三种灵长类。
Okay? The first is gorillas.
好的？第一种是大猩猩。
We also look at chimpanzees.
我们也研究黑猩猩。
And we look at binaural bowls.
我们还研究双耳碗。
Okay? Chimpanzees and binaural bowls are very close to us.
好的？黑猩猩和双耳碗与我们非常接近。
Genetically they're the closest to us of all the primates.
在基因上它们是所有灵长类中最接近我们的。
So, by looking at these four different fields we're
所以，通过研究这四个不同的种类我们可以……
able to collect evidence to construct theories as
能够收集证据来构建理论
to why we transitioned from hunter -gatherer into farming.
为什么我们从狩猎采集转向农耕
Okay? So now I will share some of these theories with you. And
好的？现在我会跟你分享其中的一些理论。
again what's really important to understand is we don't know what happened.
再次，真正重要的是我们不知道发生了什么。
We can only guess about what happened.
我们只能猜测发生了什么。
So the first theory is the idea of coercion.
第一个理论是强制的概念。
okay. And what this basically means is that
好的。基本上这意味着……
there's an elite group of people who didn't want to work
有一群精英人不想工作……
So they made everyone else work
于是他们让其他人工作
Okay, so that's coercion and the evidence for this is
好的，以上就是强制，证据是……
that well guess what?
那好，猜什么？
Gorillas do this right?
大猩猩就是这么做的吧？
If you study gorillas, you will see that
如果你研究大猩猩，你会发现……
they always have an alpha male
它们总是有一个主雄性……
The male who's bigger than everyone else and who
那位比其他人都大的雄性……
makes everyone do all the work He just sits and
让大家都干完工，他自己坐着睡觉，但他得到所有女孩和所有食物
naps every day, but he gets all the girls and he gets all the food
好的，猴子们，那是第一个理论。
Okay, so gorillas That's the first theory.
第二个理论是战争。
The second theory is
第二个理论是
War Okay,
战争，好吧，
and The idea here is that
而这里的想法是
if you are on a farm It's easier to protect yourself in a time of war
如果你在农场，战争时更容易自保
and you're out in the force, right?
而你在外面，没错吧？
You can build walls around your farm
你可以在农场周围筑墙
you can Defend yourself a lot easier.
你可以更容易地自保。
You can see the enemy coming Okay, so
你可以看到敌人来临，好吧，接着说。
War the evidence for this is that chimpanzees.
战争的证据是猿类。
Okay again who are like us
好的，再说一次，像我们这样的人
They go to war a lot.
他们经常打仗
They're very violent. They're always fighting each other
他们很暴力，常常互相打斗
So the argument here is that
所以这里的论点是
we human beings are just a violent
我们人类只是个暴力的
People who are always at war and
人，总是处在战争中
we Must be afraid of each other and
我们彼此相互恐惧，随后有机会便会定居、筑城墙、相互争斗。
therefore when we have the chance we'll settle down Build fortifications build walls
and fight each other.
我们彼此相互恐惧，随后有机会便会定居、筑城墙、相互争斗。
Okay That's the second theory and
好的，这是第二个理论，且
again the evidence for this are chimpanzees.
再次的证据是猕猴。
The third theory is
第三个理论是
respect for
敬老
elders Meaning
老人的意义
that as a hunter -gatherer
作为狩猎采集者
It's very hard on
很难照顾老人，吧？
Old people, right? so
老年人，吧？
at a certain point
在某个时点
you're gonna have to leave the old people to just stay there and die and
你们得把老人留在那里，让他们在那里住着然后去死吧
Maybe we as human beings we are
也许我们人类本身是……
biologically programmed to take care of elders for whatever reason,
生物学上我们被编程去照顾老人，原因不明
okay, and again, the evidence for this is
好的，再说一次，这一说法的证据是……
Anthropology where every culture respects its elders, right?
人类学里每个文化都尊敬老人，对吧？
So that's a third theory The last
所以这就是第三个说法，最后一个
theory is religion The last theory is religion
理论是宗教，最后一个理论是宗教
Okay, meaning that
好的，意思是……
we settle down in order to
我们在秩序中安定下来
celebrate a religion to practice a religion and
庆祝宗教，实践宗教，且…
Just to be clear
仅作说明…
There's evidence and arguments for all four theories
有证据与论据支持四种说法…
and there are scholars who argued for different theories Okay,
并且有学者为不同理论作出论证，好吧，
but the consensus what most people?
但大多数人达成共识的是今天的结论，】】
agree on today,
}
okay, most scholars not every scholar, but most scholars is
好的，绝大多数学者而非每位学者，但大多数学者是…
Religion, okay, so
宗教，好的，接着说…
let me explain why we think the answer has to be religion slowly.
让我慢慢解释为什么我们认为答案一定是宗教。
All right, okay so
好的，接着说，
coercion While it is true
强制化，虽然确实如此
that with gorillas, there's an alpha male
在大猩猩中，存在主导雄性
Who controls everything?
谁掌控一切？
the problem is That
问题是那样
if you look at gorilla's the
看猩猩时
alpha male is huge Okay,
α雄性很大，好的，
and males are a lot bigger than females
雄性比雌性大很多
So
所以
it's possible for one gorilla to exert force
一只大猩猩可以施加力量
and pressure on the others.
并对其他人施加压力。
Okay with human beings That's harder, right? Because
好的，和人类相比更难，对吧？因为
let's just say a nine -foot giant human being comes into this room
让我们说一个九英尺高的人类出现进来这个房间
and It's like I'm now your brother Boss you have to you have to go for me.
就像我现在是你的兄弟，老板，你得去为我做事。
You have to give me all your woman. Okay, what can we do as a class?
你得把你所有的女人给我。好了，班上我们能做什么？
Beat the crap out of him. Okay, you understand because
把他打得干干净净。好的，你明白了，因为
we have big brains and
我们有大脑袋，
these big brains allow us to cooperate together Okay,
这些大脑袋让我们能一起合作
so this guy's around and
于是这个人出现了，
at first we're afraid of him So we let him do whatever he wants,
一开始我们怕他，于是让他随便做，
but then he goes to bed and then and then we have to class discuss Hey, what can we do?
然后他去睡觉，接着我们要开讨论：嘿，我们能做什么？
Well, we can make weapons, right?
好，我们可以制造武器，对吧？
Or we can trap him?
或者我们可以把他困住？
Or we can trick him we can give him poison food
或者我们可以用计谋，给他投毒食？
Okay, so coercion
好的，先说一下强制
Among humans is Very very hard to
在人类中非常非常难做最坏的情况
do the worst case scenario scenario.
做最坏的情况
We can't beat him up. What we'll do is just run away
我们没法打败他。我们要做的就是跑掉
Okay, does that make sense? So
好的，这样说通吗？于是
we don't think portion is an explanation
我们认为部分也不是解释
Because there's so many ways for us to fight back
因为有很多方法可以反击
and to rebel against
并且可以反叛
bigger people, okay so
更大的人
Quarantine doesn't really work war
隔离并不真正起作用于战争
Okay, so
好了，接着说
We don't think war is a good explanation either
我们也认为战争不是一个好的解释
So it is true that chimpanzees are
于是，黑猿确实是天生的
Naturally violent. Okay, they're always being the crap out of each other
他们总是互相打闹
But guess what? bonobos
但你猜怎么了？狒猴
Who are actually closer to us genetically than chimpanzees?
谁在基因上比黑猿更接近我们？
They're actually very peaceful.
它们实际上非常和平。
They don't fight each other
它们互相不打架。
Okay, so there's no evidence that we human beings are
好的，已经没有证据表明我们人类本身是自然的暴力者
naturally violent
也就是说如果是战争的话…
Also if it is war
then we should be able to find weapons
然后我们应该能找到武器
And we don't really find weapons,
而我们确实没找到武器
okay in archaeology We don't really find weapons of early human history
在考古学里我们确实没找到早期人类的武器
okay okay
好的好的
okay okay okay okay okay
好的好的好的好的好的
okay okay okay okay okay okay okay okay okay okay okay okay okay okay
好的好的好的好的好的好的好的好的好的好的好的
okay okay okay okay okay
好的好的好的好的好的
okay okay okay
好的好的好的
Now it's possible that in the future we'll find evidence,
现在有可能在未来我们会找到证据，
but I'm just saying that right now, in archeology and anthropology,
但我现在只是说，在考古学和人类学里，
we do not have any evidence, okay?
我们还没有任何证据，好的？
The last, then we look at respect for elders.
最后，我们再看对长辈的敬重。
And even though this is a valid theory,
即便这是一种有效的理论，
there's an argument that back
还有一种反驳说回……
then they didn't really care about dying that much.
然后他们并不太在意死亡。
And the reason why is that
原因是这样的
for most of human history,
在大部分人类历史里，
we human beings have seen life,
我们人类已经把生命看成一个圆环，没错吗？
history as a circle, right?
比如说，现在是夏天，……
So for example, right now it's summer,
it's gonna turn into fall, then winter, then spring,
它会变成秋天，然后是冬天，再是春天，
then summer again, okay?
然后又是夏天，好吗？
So the world, history,
于是世界，历史，
moves in a cycle.
它在循环中移动。
Well human life also moves in a cycle.
人类的生命也在循环中移动。
You're born, you're born, you die,
你出生，你出生，你死亡。
then you're reborn,
然后你重生，
then you die again, then you're reborn again, okay?
然后你再次死亡，再次重生，好吗？
So back then, they really didn't care if you died.
于是回到那时，他们真的不在乎你是否死亡。
In fact, if you're an old person, you're probably like,
实际上，如果你是老人，可能会是这样，我更愿意死去，那么如果我死了，我就会重生或进入灵界，行吗？
you know what, I'd rather be dead, and then,
so if I die, I'll either be reborn or go into the spirit world, okay?
实际上，如果你是老人，可能会是这样，我更愿意死去，那么如果我死了，我就会重生或进入灵界，行吗？
So they didn't really fear death, or they really didn't see death like the way we saw death.
于是他们对死亡并不真正恐惧，也不把死亡看成我们所见的那样。
Yeah? What is the evidence for death?
嗯？死亡的证据是什么？
Okay, that's a great question, okay?
好的，这是个很好的问题。
So the evidence for this is what we understand about their religion,
因此，这一证据来自我们对他们宗教的理解，
which we will discuss later on and in next class, okay?
我们稍后在下一节课里再讨论，好的？
All right, the last, so that leaves religion
好了，最后一个，剩下的是宗教
as the most likely possibility.
作为最有可能的情况。
And this, again, this is what most scholars believe happen.
再说一次，这就是大多数学者认为发生的事。
And so we're gonna look at three different archeological sites.
于是我们将去看三个不同的考古遗址。
The first is Copeca Tepe.
第一个是科佩卡塔佩。
The second is Jericho. And the third is Catahoyac, okay?
第二个是耶利哥。第三个是卡塔霍亚克，好吗？
All right, so I'm gonna draw up a,
好了，我要画一个……
we'll first see a picture of Copeca Tepe.
我们先来看看科佩卡塔佩的照片。
And guys, these places were only discovered
伙计们，这些地方是最近几十年才被发现的。
in the past few decades,
in the past fewdecades,
okay? So these are new places. We're only starting to understand these places.
好的？这些是新发现的地方。我们才刚开始了解它们。
And so this place is in Turkey, in central Turkey.
这个地方在土耳其中部。
And this dates back to about 9500 BC.
它的年代约在公元前9500年。
So this is about over 11,000 years old.
于是，这个地方已有11000多年的历史。
And we don't even think this is the oldest place, okay?
我们甚至不认为它是最古老的地方，行吗？
So if you did your research, you will know that
如果你做过研究，你就会知道。
this is basically a place of religious worship.
这基本是一个宗教崇拜的场所。
You can see that they constructed this place
你可以看到他们建造了这个场所
so that there are these T -shaped holes.
于是出现了这些T形孔洞。
These are the T -shaped pillars, okay? And these things are huge, right?
这些是T形柱子，行吗？这些东西很大，对吧？
This is a human being and this is a T -shaped pillar, okay?
这是一个人，这是一根T形柱子，行吗？
We think, again, this is all theory, okay?
我们认为，这又是理论，行吗？
This is all what we know.
这就是我们所知的一切。
We don't know that much because this is all recent, okay? But we think that
我们不太清楚，因为这只是最近的事，行吗？但我们认为……
these T -shapes represent human beings,
这些T形结构代表人类。
okay? And within these T -shapes are animals.
好的？在这些T形结构里还有动物。
And you can see that they align,
你可以看到它们排列着，
you know, they're not, you know, they're not exactly the same.
你知道，它们不是完全一样的。
This is where we think that that makes sense.
这就是我们认为有意义的地方。
This is where we think that that makes sense. This is where we think that that makes sense.
这就是我们认为有意义的地方。这就是我们认为有意义的地方。
This is where we think that that makes sense.
这就是我们认为有意义的地方。
This is where we think that that makes sense. This is where we think that that makes sense.
这就是我们认为有意义的地方。这就是我们认为有意义的地方。
This is where we think that that makes sense.
这就是我们认为有意义的地方。
is a place of religious worship.
是一个宗教崇拜的场所。
Now what's interesting about Gobeitepe is
现在，关于Gobeitepe有趣的地方是
that the religious site is the oldest,
那座宗教场所是最古老的，
but we also find houses that are built later on.
但我们也发现后期建造的房屋。
So what we think might have happened here is that
于是我们认为这里可能发生了……
hunter -gatherers will come to a place now
猎人-采集者会来到一个地方
and then to practice religion because
然后去实践宗教，因为
ultimately as human beings,
最终作为人类，
and we discussed this last class,
我们在上节课讨论过这个问题，
we have a yearning or we have a need to understand why.
我们有一种渴求或需要去理解它的原因。
And religion solves this problem for us.
宗教为我们解决了这个问题。
Also, as hunter -gatherer,
另外，作为猎人-采集者，
you need to associate with other hunter -gatherers in order to find mates,
你需要与其他猎人-采集者结伴，以便寻找配偶，
to find husbands and wives to reproduce.
以便找到丈夫和妻子来繁衍。
And so this sort of religious center, it's a great time to come
于是这类宗教中心，来此练习信仰正是好时机，
and practice your religion, but
但也是聚餐的好时机。
it's also a great time to feast and
to meet someone you can marry and have children with.
去遇见可以结婚并生孩子的人。
So that
于是如此。
was the original function of the temple.
这就是寺庙最初的功能。
Now these places are often led by shamans.
现在这些地方往往由巫师领袖。
And what makes them special is that they are charismatic leaders.
而使它们特别的，是它们是有魅力的领袖。
Okay? Charismatic leaders.
好？有魅力的领袖。
Charismatic leaders are people like Mao Zedong,
具有魅力的领袖像毛泽东、巴拉克·奥巴马、比尔·克林顿，好的？
Barack Obama, Bill Clinton, okay?
他们是那种人，因各种原因，...
They're people who for whatever reason,
They're people whofor whatever reason,
people just love them and want to follow them.
人们只是喜欢他们，想跟随他们。
Okay? And so maybe what happened was
好？于是也许是这样发生的。
that these charismatic leaders,
这些有魅力的领袖，
they built this place and they became like celebrities.
他们建造了这个地方，随后便成了名人。
And people came from all over to meet them,
人们从四面八方赶来与他们相会，
to hear the religion,
去聆听那宗教的教义。
and to meet other people.
并与其他人相会。
And over time,
并且随着时间的推移，
some people even chose to stay with them
有些人甚至选择与他们同住。
and build houses to celebrate them.
建造房屋以庆祝他们。
Okay? And then when they died,
好了？随后他们去世后，
what happened was they still worshiped them in their death.
所发生的事是他们仍在死后祭祀他们。
And so this place became a temple.
于是这地方变成了寺庙。
Okay? Does that make sense? So
好？这有道理吗？于是……
that's one theory about Kobayatepe.
这就是关于科巴亚特佩的一个理论。
There are other theories. Okay?
还有其他理论。好？
There are some people who will tell you that space aliens came down
有些人会告诉你，外星人降临并建造了这个地方，因为它很精巧。
and built this place because it's so sophisticated.
Okay? But, so there are different theories.
好？但，确实有不同的理论。
But the one that scholars most agree with today,
但目前学者最一致的说法是，
okay, is that it was a religious center.
好，认为它是一个宗教中心。
Any questions before I move on to, before I move on?
还有问题吗？我继续讲吗？
So this means that religions were honored?
这意味着宗教被尊崇了吗？
Yes. Okay.
好的，答案是这样。
So that's a great question.
那是个很好的问题。
Okay? Where does religion come from?
好？宗教从哪里来？
And this is something that we will look at very closely next class.
接下来一节课我们会仔细研究这个。
And the answer is this.
答案就是这样。
Okay. Even though
好的。虽然如此，
we all have the need for religion,
我们都需要宗教。
we don't all have the ability to produce religion.
我们并非都具备创作宗教的能力。
Okay? So who these charismatic leaders are,
好？那么这些有魅力的领袖是谁呢？
are people who
他们就是人们……
have visions or dreams of God.
有关于上帝的异象或梦境。
Okay? Or the spirit world.
好？或者关于灵界的异象。
Okay? And then they present their visions to other people.
好？随后他们把自己的异象呈现给他人。
And we have people like this throughout human history.
我们在整个人类历史中都有类似的人物。
Right? So think of Jesus.
好？想想耶稣。
Think of Mohammed.
想想穆罕默德。
Think of Buddha. Think of Confucius.
想想佛陀。想想孔子。
Right? These are people who
好？这些人是……
have these visions of God or of spirituality
他们拥有关于上帝或灵性的异象。
or of a new world and present to people.
或是新世界的愿景并呈现给人们。
And because they're charismatic, they're able to attract followers and spread their religion.
而且因为他们有魅力，能吸引追随者并传播其宗教。
And that's what probably happened here as well.
这大概也是此处所发生的情形。
Because as you can see from this picture,
因为从这张图可以看出，
it was very hard work to build this temple.
建这座寺庙是一件非常艰苦的事。
Okay? This is 11,000 years ago.
好了？这已经是11000年前的事了。
They didn't have bulldozers.
他们没有推土机。
They didn't have shovels.
他们没有铲子。
Okay? This is all by hand.
好了？全靠手工。
So for them to want to dedicate their lives to building this temple,
于是他们愿意把一生奉献给建这座寺庙，
because it took a long time.
因为这需要很长时间。
It took years and years and hundreds of people.
耗费了多年，数百人。
Well, you needed something called religious devotion.
好吧，你们需要一种叫做宗教奉献的东西。
Faith. Does that make sense?
信仰。这样说通吗？
Okay? And again, throughout human history, we've seen this.
好的？再说一次，纵观人类历史，我们都看到了这一点。
Right? So think of Christians. Think of Buddhists.
对吧？想想基督徒。想想佛教徒。
Think of Muslims.
想想穆斯林。
Religious faith. So that's what built this.
宗教信仰。于是这才建成。
Okay? So does that answer your question?
好的？那就回答了你的问题吗？
Yes. Okay. Any more questions before I continue?
是。好的。继续之前还有别的问题吗？
Yes?.
是？
Okay. So that's a good question.
好的。那是个好问题。
Why is a temple structured like this?
为什么寺庙会这样结构？
Okay? And the answer is that
好的？答案是这样。
there's cosmological significance
有宇宙学意义
to the structure.
在结构中。
Meaning that on a certain time of the year,
意味着在一年中的某个时刻，
what will happen is that
事情会是这样：太阳会以某种方式照射到这个地方。
the sun will hit this place in a certain way.
于是它几乎像个钟表。
So it's almost like a clock.
这就是它的作用。
Does that make sense to you guys?
你们觉得这样有道理吗？
They designed this in a way so they can tell time.
他们把它设计成可以用来计时的样子。
But their intention was not to tell time.
但他们的目的并不是用来计时。
Their intention was to connect with the outer world.
他们的意图是与外部世界相连。
Right? Does that make sense to you guys?
对吧？你们觉得这样有道理吗？
So they were extremely sophisticated.
于是他们非常精巧。
They knew a lot about the way the stars worked.
他们对星星的运行方式了解很多。
Okay? So basically, for them, this is science.
好吧？基本上，对他们来说，这就是科学。
Okay? Today we say this is a religion.
好吧？今天我们说这是一种宗教。
But their science back then is no different from our science today.
但当时的科学和今天的科学没有区别。
Okay? Does that answer your question?
好吧？这回答了你的问题吗？
Okay. And you had a question? .
好的。你还有问题吗？
Okay. So if you talk to any religious people, they saw it.
好的。只要你跟任何宗教人士说话，他们就会看到它。
Okay? They were there.
好的？他们就在那儿。
They talked to God. Right?
他们跟上帝说话。对吧。
So we're like, well, you know, that doesn't make any sense.
于是我们说，嗯，你知道，这样说没啥意义。
But they really believe it.
但他们真的相信。
And that's why they're able to convince their followers.
这就是他们能说服众的原因。
Okay? So in the future, we will look at someone like Muhammad
好的？那么在未来，我们会去看像穆罕默德这样的人。
who had religious visions in a cave.
他在洞里有宗教异象。
And you're like, did he really see an angel?
你会问，他真的看见天使了吗？
Well, he thought he really did.
好吧，他真的以为自己做到了。
Okay? And
好？而且
in fact, in our research,
事实上，在我们的研究中
what we discovered is that people who use something called the
我们发现的是，使用一种叫做“迷幻剂”的人。好？你知道迷幻剂是什么吗？
psychedelics. Okay? Do you know what psychedelics are?
迷幻剂是药物。是什么药物？
Psychedelics are drugs. What drugs, and
what these drugs do is they shift your neural system
这些药物的作用是让你的神经系统发生变化，从而你以不同的方式感知世界。
so that you see the world in a different way.
当你这样做时，你就能看到不同的景象。
When you do that, you're able to have different visions.
Okay? But we also know that
好的？但我们也知道，
if you go hungry for a long time or you meditate for a long time,
如果你长时间饿着或者长时间冥想，
you're able to see different things.
你就能看到不同的事物。
So from their perspective, they actually saw this thing.
从他们的视角来看，他们确实看到了这件事。
Okay? Even though like we don't think it actually happened.
好？虽然我们觉得这件事并未真正发生。
Does that make sense? For them, it's true.
这样说通吗？对他们来说，这是真的。
But maybe for us, it's not so true.
但对我们来说，可能并非如此。
Okay? All right. Any more questions before I go on?
好？好了。还有别的问题吗？
All right. So
好了。
these are great questions.
这些是很好的问题。
And keep on asking them.
继续问下去。
Okay? And these are hard questions that we will go over the next few classes.
好的，这些是我们接下来几节课要讨论的难题。
So let me show you another picture. Okay?
好了，我再给你展示一张图。好吗？
This is what is in the pillars at Goblete Tepe.
这就是在戈布莱特佩柱子里的样子。
Okay? Now,
好了？
what's really interesting about these pictures,
这些图像真正有趣的地方是……
okay, is that these are animals
好了，关键是这些是动物……
in the motion of hunting.
它们正处于狩猎动作中。
So the fox, right?
所以狐狸，没错吧？
The way the fox hunts is the fox jumps up in the air
狐狸的捕猎方式是先跳到空中
and then goes down. And attacks the prey.
然后落下，攻击猎物。
So this is in the motion of attack.
于是它们正处于攻击动作中。
Why would they do that?
他们为什么要这么做？
What's the point of having animals on these pillars?
把动物放在这些柱子上有什么意义？
Why would they do that?
他们为什么要这么做？
Good. Okay. Yes. Okay.
好的。好的。是的。好的。
So what's really important to understand is
于是要真正理解的是
that back then, and again, I'll explain to you what I mean.
那时再回去，再次，我会把我的意思告诉你。
I'll explain to you over the next couple of weeks.
接下来几周，我会再给你解释。
Back then,
那时再回去。
we human beings did not see us as separate from the other world.
我们人类没有把自己视为与其他世界分离。
Okay? Does that make sense? Animals, trees,
好的？这有道理吗？动物、树木、人类，皆同等。
humans, all equal.
So first of all, if you're going to kill these animals,
首先，如果你要杀这些动物，
you need to ask for their forgiveness.
你需要请求它们的赦免。
Otherwise, their spirit, their soul will haunt you.
否则，它们的灵魂会跟随你。
Okay? They'll take revenge on you.
好的？他们会报仇。
So if you kill these animals, you're going to get a reward.
所以如果你杀了这些动物，你会得到回报。
If you kill them, you must ask for their forgiveness.
如果你杀了它们，你必须请求它们的赦免。
Okay? And the one way to do that is by paying tribute to them.
好吧？做这件事的唯一方式就是向它们献上贡品。
Okay? That's number one. Number two is
好的？第一点是。第二点是
that we can learn from these animals.
我们可以从这些动物身上学到的事。
Right? They're the best hunters in the world.
对吧？它们是世界上最好的猎手。
So before we go on a hunting trip,
所以在我们去打猎之旅之前，
we might have a ceremony to channel their energy
我们可能会举行仪式来通灵它们的能量。
and power and wisdom.
以及力量与智慧。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这样说通吗？好的？
And the third thing is basically, you know, you're going to have to be a hunter.
第三点基本上是，你知道，你将要成为猎人。
Basically, to appease them or to become their friends.
基本上，安抚他们或成为他们的朋友。
Because we don't want to hunt foxes.
因为我们不想猎捕狐狸。
We want to hunt gazelle.
我们想猎捕羚羊。
There's more meat than gazelle. They're easier to capture.
比羚羊更有肉量，捕捉更容易。
But we want to be friends with the gazelle.
我们想和羚羊成为朋友。
We want to be friends with the lion.
我们想和狮子成为朋友。
Okay? We don't want to be enemies.
好的？我们不想成为敌人。
So, it's a sign of respect to the animals.
于是，向动物致敬意就是一种礼貌的标志。
So that's basically their religion. And
于是，这基本就是他们的宗教。然后
coming together at the religious festival was
在宗教节日聚集在一起
about celebrating their relationship with these animals
关于庆祝与这些动物的关系
as well as channeling their power,
以及运用它们的力量
their energy and their wisdom so that they could go hunt as well.
他们的精力与智慧，以便能去狩猎。
Does that make sense? So this is probably one of the earlier religions that we have.
这样说通吗？这大概是我们已知的早期宗教之一。
Is this clear to you guys so far?
到目前为止，你们觉得清楚吗？
All right. All right. Let's move on.
好的，好的。我们继续。
Okay. So now this is Jericho.
好的。现在这就是耶利哥。
And Jericho is part of something called the Natufian culture.
耶利哥属于被称为纳图菲安文化的一个体系。
And the Natufian culture appeared about 13,000 years ago or even more actually,
纳图菲安文化大约在一万三千年前出现，甚至更早。
maybe 15,000 years ago in a place we call the Levant.
大约1万5千年前，在我们称之为黎凡特的地方。
The Levant is basically the Middle East, Israel and Syria.
黎凡特基本上就是中东、以色列和叙利亚。
And what was special about the Natufian culture are three things.
纳图菲安文化的三大特色是：
First. First of all, they were sedentary.
首先，第一点，他们是定居的。
Okay. Sedentary basically means that
好的。定居基本上是指他们……
they basically stayed in one place.
好的。他们基本上停留在同一地点。
Okay. Remember, hunter -gatherers, they roamed around.
好的。记住，狩猎采集者，他们四处游走。
They moved from place to place. But
他们从一个地方搬到另一个地方。
they were hunter -gatherers who were sanitary.
他们是四处游走的狩猎采集者。
Okay. They were not farmers.
好的。他们不是农民。
They were hunter -gatherers. But they stayed in one place.
他们是狩猎采集者，但他们定居在同一地点。
And the reason why we know, there's a lot of evidence, but
我们知道的原因有很多证据。
one reason why we know is that they basically hunted gazelles.
一个原因是他们基本上是猎捕角马的。
Gazelles are like deers, right? And
角马像鹿一样，对吧？而且
the thing about gazelles is their teeth color is different according to the season.
角马的牙色随季节变化。
So in the summer and in the winter, because they eat different foods.
于是夏季和冬季，他们吃不同的食物。
Okay. So the teeth color is different.
好的，所以牙色不同。
So we're able to dig up these gazelle bones, look at the teeth and recognize that, oh,
于是我们可以挖出这些角马骨头，观察牙齿并认出它们。
they were hunting gazelle in this area both in the summer
他们在这个地区夏季也在狩猎角马。
and the winter, which meant they did not move.
在冬季，他们也不迁徙。
Okay. So they were sedentary.
好的。所以他们是定居的。
That's the first thing.
第一点是这样。
Second thing is that they had domesticated crops.
第二点是他们已经驯化了农作物。
And the reason why we know is we're able to dig up seeds of crops.
于是我们能挖出作物种子，知道它们的存在。
Okay. Vegetables and wheat and
好了。蔬菜、麦子等作物。
barley, which meant that they had the capacity,
大麦，这意味着他们具备种植的能力，
the technology to farm, but they chose not to farm.
但他们选择不去种植。
Does that make sense? Okay.
这有道理吗？好了。
So basically, the way they developed this technology is for gardening.
基本上，他们发展这项技术的方式就是种菜。
Right. They were hunting -gathering.
对了。他们是狩猎采集。
They were hunting -gathering most of the time. But some of them, for fun, for pleasure, had their own garden.
他们大部分时间是狩猎采集。但有些人，出于乐趣，自己种了花园。
And that's how they developed the technology.
于是他们就这样发展了技术。
Okay. And the third thing
好的，第三点是……
that
那点
was very important is they had something
很重要的是他们有个东西
called the cult of the skull.
叫做“头骨崇拜”
Okay. So
好的。于是
they probably worshipped animals,
他们大概会崇拜动物，
but they also worshipped ancestors.
他们也会崇拜祖先。
And the reason why we think so is because they worshipped animals. Right.
并且我们之所以这么认为，是因为他们崇拜动物。对。
Right. Right. Right.
对。对。对。
Right. Right. Right. Right.
对。对。对。对。
Right. Right.
对。对。
Right. Right. Right. Right.
对。对。对。对。
Right. Right. Right.
对。对。对。
Right. Right.
对。对。
Right. and it's called the Tower of Jericho.
对。并且它叫作耶利米塔楼。
When we first discovered this, we thought, oh,
当我们第一次发现它时，我们想，哦，
this must be a evidence
这必须是证据
that Jericho went to war, okay?
耶利米塔城曾经战争，行吗？
Because it had walls and it had a tower, right?
因为它有墙和塔，对吧？
The walls are to protect you from your enemies.
墙是用来保护你免受敌人之害。
The tower is to see your enemies coming.
塔是用来观察敌人来临。
But then they did more research and realized that, oh, no,
但随后他们做了更多研究，才发现，哦，没错。
no, no, this tower is a religious monument.
不不，这座塔是宗教纪念碑。
It is the same as Gobletepe where it is cosmological,
它与戈布莱特佩一样，具有宇宙学意义，
meaning that at the longest day of the year,
即在一年中最长的一天，
the mountain over here will cast
这里的山会投下
a shadow over the tower.
塔上投下阴影。
The tower will cast a shadow over the entire village,
塔会把阴影投到整个村庄。
covering it all up in darkness.
把它全部覆盖在黑暗里。
Okay? Does that make sense, you guys?
好的？这样说通吗，你们？
Why would they wanna do that?
他们为什么要这么做？
What does that do for you?
这对你有什么好处？
To have the entire village cover up in darkness?
让整个村庄全被黑暗覆盖？
Any guesses? Why would they do that?
有什么猜测吗？他们为什么这么做？
Excuse me? What do you mean by that?
请问？你这句话是什么意思？
..!
……！
. I know,
我知道，
but if that were the case, you'd just move, right?
但如果是那样，你就会搬过去，对吗？
So, okay, so what's really important is that
所以，好的，最重要的是
this is like right after the last ice age, okay?
这就像是刚好在上一次冰河之后，行吗？
So it's actually pretty cold.
所以实际上挺冷的。
Okay? They did this for religious reasons, right?
好吧？他们这么做是出于宗教原因，对吧？
Because when you cover your village in darkness, you feel as
因为当你把村庄覆上黑暗时，你会觉得自己与天空相连。
though you are in connection with the sky.
就像你与天空相连一样。
Does that make sense? So they must have a religious belief.
这有道理吗？所以他们一定有宗教信仰。
They must have a religious belief in which part of the worship is to cover the village in darkness.
他们的宗教信仰中，祭祀的一部分就是把村庄覆上黑暗。
..
…
.......
……
...
…
..
. This makes
这有道理
sense. This
意思。此
makes sense.
此有道理。
This makes sense.
Okay So they design a tower in a certain way
好的，所以他们以某种方式设计了塔
So that it would cover the village in darkness
以便让它把村庄覆盖在黑暗之中
and they could see that as magic and that's evidence
于是他们把这看作魔法，便成了证据
that your religion is correct Does that make sense?
那你的宗教是正确的，这有道理吗？
Right these otherwise, how do you know your religion is correct?
好吧，除此之外，你怎么知道你的宗教是正确的？
Only by performing magic.
只有通过施展魔法。
Can you show that this charismatic leader?
你能展示这位有魅力的领袖吗？
Okay, who came up this idea?
好的，谁提出了这个想法？
It speaks to God Okay, does that make sense?
它向上帝说话，好的，这有道理吗？
Okay, so let's look at sort of pictures of skulls.
好的，让我们先看看几张骷髅的图片。
Okay, because this was actually very common back then
好的，因为那时这件事其实很常见。
Okay, so basically this is a skull they covered up with clay
基本上这是一块被粘土覆盖的骷髅。
and they carried around with them all over the place and this Is true throughout the world at that time.
并且他们把它们随身携带到各处，这在当时的世界各地都是真实的。
Okay, and just answer worship Okay
好的，接着回答敬拜吧。
So this is another picture of the skull
这又是一张骷髅的图片。
Skull okay. Let me ask you why they would do that
骷髅，好吗？让我问问他们为什么会这么做
Their ancestors dead. Why would they do that?
他们的祖先已逝。为什么他们会这么做？
Why would they have to skull around?
他们为什么要把骷髅带在身边？
Where's the ancestors now?
祖先现在在哪里？
Where's the dead person? Where's the dead person?
死者在哪里？死者在哪里？
The spirit ward right someplace in another world
灵魂守护在另一个世界的某处
and therefore having a skull around allows you to communicate with
并且拥有一个骷髅在身边可以让你与之沟通
that world and learn its secrets
那世界并且能让你领悟其奥秘
You understand and
你已明白
some of the secrets may be like how to construct a tower in a way
一些秘密可能像是怎样以某种方式建造塔楼
That you're able to cast a shadow over the village
你能把影子投在村子上
Okay, so that's their method But then we also have the idea of scientific discovery
好的，那就是他们的方法，但我们也有科学发现的概念
Does that make sense to communicate with the spirit world through for your ancestors?
这有意义吗？通过它与祖先的灵界沟通？
Does that make sense? Okay, the point I'm going to tell you is that
这有意义吗？好了，我要说的重点是……
Their level of intelligence or their understand the world.
他们的智力水平或对世界的理解。
It's just as sophisticated as artists in the world.
它就像世界里的艺术家一样精巧。
Okay There's that we think
好的，我们认为
that when we go to science class we're learning facts and
当我们去上科学课时，我们在学事实
Knowledge but guess what?
知识，但你猜怎么回事？
Maybe a thousand years from now? people will look at our science,
大约一千年后？人们会看我们的科学，像物理学，然后说，哦，那也是一种宗教。
like the physics, and be like, oh, that was a religion too.
Does that make sense? So, in terms of intelligence,
这有道理吗？从智力上说，
they were just as creative and as sophisticated as we are today,
他们和我们今天一样有创造力和精巧，
but they just had a different set of beliefs.
只是他们的信仰体系不同。
Alright, so the last place I want to look at is Kanahoyak, okay? So Kanahoyak,
好的，接下来我想看的地方是卡纳霍亚克，好吗？
Kanahoyak is a huge place, okay, in Turkey as well,
卡纳霍亚克是一个很大的地方，好吗，位于土耳其也，
pretty far from Gopalantepe, but about the same place.
它离戈帕兰特佩相当远，但大致在同一地区。
And this dates back about 7500 BCE.
它的年代约在公元前7500年。
And as you can see, it's a huge village.
正如你所见，它是一个大村落。
And we think that, at its height, okay,
我们认为，在它的鼎盛时期，
maybe this was around for about 2,000 years, but at its height of development, of civilization,
也许它存在了大约两千年，但在鼎盛时期，文明发展到极点时，约有八千人。
it had about 8,000 people.
大约八千人。
That's a lot of people, guys, okay?
这可是很多人，大家好啊？
And the thing about Kanahoyak
以及关于卡纳霍亚克的事
that stands out is, first of all, it's huge, okay?
首先，它很大，好的？
Second of all,
其次，
they didn't have a place of worship or government,
他们没有专门的祭祀或政府场所，好的？意思是所有房屋都一样。
okay? Meaning that all the houses were the same.
它是一个非常平等的社会。
It was a very egalitarian society.
Everyone was the same. And what's even more interesting is
人人都一样。更有趣的是
that if you go to every house,
如果你去每间房子，
there's a site, the living room is basically a temple unto itself.
有一个地方，客厅基本就是自己的寺庙。
It was a place of worship and religion, okay?
它是一个祭祀与宗教的场所，好的？
Meaning that the first,
意思是最初的，
like, Kanahoyak is a place where
像，Kanahoyak是一个场所
religion permeated, okay, the temple.
宗教渗透进了，好的，寺庙。
It was in every place.
它存在于每一个地方。
They were, okay? So we think
他们是这样，好的？所以我们认为
that Kanahoyak is one of the first religious communities.
那是Kanahoyak是最早的宗教社群之一。
Remember that before, religious sites or places you went to,
记得以前，宗教场所或你去过的地方，
maybe once in your lifetime or maybe once a year, okay?
可能一辈子一次，或者一年一次，好的？
But it wasn't part of your everyday life.
但它并不是你日常生活的一部分。
Whereas in Kanahoyak,
而在Kanahoyak，
religion was in your life from birth to death,
宗教从出生到死亡贯穿你的生活。
okay? So, you know, it's a very, very, very, very, very, okay, okay. Does that makes sense.
好的？所以，你知道，真是非常非常非常非常非常好，好的，好的。这样说通吗。
And the think about Kanahoyak that's very interesting is at this point,
而且关于Kanahoyak的想法，最有趣味的就是此时，
their religion is extremely sophisticated.
他们的宗教极为精巧。
Meaning that they can explain everything using their religion.
意思是他们可以用宗教来解释一切。
Okay. So their everyday life
好的。所以他们的日常生活
and their religion was completely aligned together.
以及他们的宗教完全一致。
So let me show you some evidence of this.
好了，我来给你展示一些证据。
So this is a painting that
这是一幅画，画中……
you will see in every house or most houses in Kanahoye.
你会在卡纳霍耶的每一所房子里看到它。
Okay? All right?
好的？行吗？
So you're like, what is going on here?
那你说，事情怎么回事？
So again, there are different theories.
再说一次，理论各不相同。
But let me explain to you what most scholars believe to be the accurate theories.
但让我来解释一下大多数学者认为最准确的理论。
Okay? So this is just a theory.
好？这只是一个理论。
We have no evidence for this.
我们没有证据支持这一点。
But this is what we believe. We believe
但这就是我们的信念。我们认为
that the people at Kanahoye,
在卡纳霍耶的人民
they worship a mother goddess.
他们崇拜母神。
Okay? Because a mother goddess is what gives life to everything.
好的？因为母神是赋予万物生命的存在。
Right? Think of Mother Nature.
对吧？想想大自然母亲。
Think of a woman giving birth to a child.
想想一个女人生下孩子的情景。
Okay? So they worship a mother goddess.
好的？于是他们崇拜母神。
And the mother goddess is represented by the bird.
而母神则以鸟的形象出现。
Because the bird flies all around the sky.
因为鸟在天空中自由飞翔。
Right? So the sky belongs to the bird.
对吧？于是天空归鸟所有。
Now, what is the mother goddess? Now, the bird can take different forms.
现在，母神是什么？现在，鸟可以变成不同的形态。
This is a vulture. Right?
这是一只秃鹰。对吧？
So the mother goddess can also take the form of a vulture.
于是母神也能化作秃鹰。
So what's going on here?
那到底是怎么回事？
Why is the vulture with headless people?
为什么秃鹰会跟无头人一起？
Okay? Because the way that
好的？因为他们把祖先崇拜和对母神的信仰结合起来，认为当…
they combine ancestral worship with their belief
他们把祖先崇拜与对母神的信仰结合起来，认为当…
in the mother goddess is they believe that when
a person dies, what they'll do is they'll die.
一个人去世后，他们会把他放在外面。
They'll put that person's dead body out in the open.
他们会把那个人的尸体摆在外面。
It's a sky burial. Right?
这是一种天葬。
You go to Tibet, they have sky burials.
你去西藏，他们有天葬。
The vultures will come and eat all the flesh.
秃鹰会来吃掉全肉。
And that is the tribute or the sacrifice made to the mother goddess.
这就是向母神献祭的礼物。
Okay? So the mother goddess basically cleans the body.
好的？于是母神基本把尸体清理干净。
And then you take the bones and you bury it back in your house.
然后你把骨头取出来，再把它们埋回你家里。
And you take the skull and
你把头骨取出来并……
you keep the skull in your living room to worship your ancestors.
你把头骨放在客厅里祭拜祖先。
Does that make sense?
这样说对吗？
So in other words,
换句话说，
it is an extremely comprehensive or complete religion,
它是一种极其全面或完整的宗教，
understanding the world. Okay?
理解世界。好吗？
Is that clear to you guys? What the religion is?
这宗教是什么？
Any questions so far?
到目前为止还有问题吗？
Again, by the way guys, a theory.
再说一句，顺便说一句，大家，理论。
Okay? But right now, the most useful theory
好的？但现在，最有用的理论是
that we have about this place.
我们对这个地方的了解。
Any questions before I move on?
我继续之前还有问题吗？
Okay. So.
好的。
So what's going on here? Okay?
那么这里发生了什么？好的？
Now, this again also is in Kadahoyak, many houses.
现在，这又在卡达霍亚克出现，很多房子。
So what's going on here? Okay.
那么这里发生了什么？好的。
So different scholars have different interpretations of this.
所以不同的学者对这件事有不同的解释。
Okay? Clearly, this is a hunt.
好吧？显然，这是一场狩猎。
Right? This is a hunt.
对吧？这是一场狩猎。
And. And some people believe that
而且，有些人认为
these human beings who
这些人类，正是卡达霍亚克人之一
are, you know, part of the Kadahoyak people,
are, you know, part ofthe Kadahoyak people,
they are mocking or taunting or
他们在嘲笑或挑衅或笑着对动物进行戏弄，以此来驯服它们。
laughing at the animals as a way to subdue them, to tame them.
Okay? To domesticate them.
好的？让它们驯养。
That's one theory. But another theory is that
这是一种理论。但另一种理论是
what they're really doing is dancing
他们真正做的事是舞蹈
because
因为
they are worshipping or paying tribute to these animals they are about to kill.
他们在祭拜或向即将要杀的动物献祭。
Or they are trying. So, let's go back to Kobayatepe.
或者他们在尝试。好了，回到小巴亚特佩去。
Right? Where they're trying to respect the animals.
对吧？他们正试着尊敬这些动物。
Right? Dance with you.
对吧？跟你一起舞蹈。
We're friends. I'm sorry I have to kill you.
我们是朋友。我很抱歉要杀了你。
But, hey, we're only taking your meat.
不过，嘿，我们只是拿你的肉。
Your soul. Right?
你的灵魂。对吧？
Is still going to be reborn.
它仍将重生。
Or it's going to go to the spirit world.
或者它将去往灵界。
Okay? So,
好的？那么，
this is a way of paying tribute or respecting the animals.
这是一种向动物致敬或敬畜的方式。
They're about to kill or about to hunt.
他们正要杀戮或狩猎。
To maintain the harmony of nature
保持自然的和谐
and their relationship with nature.
以及他们与自然的关系
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
这样说通吗，大家？
Again, what's really important is that
再次，真正重要的是
this is a pretty complete religion.
这是一套相当完整的宗教体系。
Right? That explains everything to these people.
对吧？这就解释了这些人所需的一切。
And that's why it's so attractive to people.
于是这才是人们如此钟爱的原因。
Right? If you're a human being, you like, you want to know why.
对吧？如果你是人类，你会想知道原因。
Well, Kadahoyak, the religion there, explains everything.
好吧，Kadahoyak那里的宗教解释了一切。
It explains why. Okay?
它解释了原因。好吗？
Does that make sense so far? Any more, any questions?
这样说通吗？还有什么？还有问题吗？
Okay. So, this is a picture of the mother goddess.
好了。于是这是一幅母神的图像。
Okay? Again, we have, we have debate about what this is.
好的？再说一次，我们有关于这是什么的争论。
Some people believe that it's just a fertility goddess.
有些人认为它只是一个生育女神。
Okay? But others believe this is the mother goddess.
好的？但也有人认为这是母神。
And you think about it.
于是你会想到它。
If you are a place like Kadahoyak,
如果你是像Kadahoyak这样的地方，
you're most concerned about giving birth.
你最关心的是生育。
Right? Because giving birth is what rejuvenates your society.
对吧？因为生育是让社会焕发活力的根源。
So, it makes sense that your god,
于是，你的神，
the person you worship the most, would be a mother goddess.
你最敬拜的那位神，
Okay? Okay?
好的？好的？
This is clearly a bull.
这明显是一头公牛。
And if you see pictures of Kadahoyak, you realize that it's a mother goddess.
如果你看到Kadahoyak的图像，你会意识到它是母神。
Okay? And you will see that they have many,
好的？你会看到他们有很多，
many depictions or pictures of bull in their house.
很多在他们的房子里出现的公牛图像或照片。
Okay? And what we believe, again, this is a theory.
好的？我们再次相信，这只是一个理论。
Okay? What we believe is that
好的吗？我们认为是这样：
if the mother goddess represents life,
如果母神代表生命，
okay, giving life, the bull represents vitality energy.
好的，赋予生命，公牛代表活力能量。
And so, it's the bull that
于是，正是那头公牛给母神注入生育之力。
gives the mother goddess the energy to give birth.
给母神注入生育之力。
Right? Does that make sense?
对吗？听得通吗？
So, the bull represents the male.
于是，公牛代表男性。
The mother goddess represents the female.
母神代表女性。
But only if the male and the female conjoin, they come together,
但只有当男性和女性结合时，他们才会在一起。
will you have life.
你将拥有生命。
Okay? So, this is another picture.
好的？所以，这又是一幅画。
Clearly, okay, they're not hunting.
显然，好的，他们不是在狩猎。
Okay? Clearly, they are worshiping the bull.
好的？显然，他们在崇拜公牛。
Does that make sense? They're paying tribute to the bull.
这有道理吗？他们在向公牛献祭。
Okay? So,
好的？
are we clear about this?
我们对此清楚吗？
How religion was a fundamental part of people's existence
宗教是人们存在的根本部分
when they chose to become sanitary.
当他们决定变得卫生时
Okay? Or they chose to settle in one place.
好的吗？或者他们选择在一个地方定居。
So, let's go back to the original question.
那么，让我们回到最初的问题。
And I'll take questions. The original question is,
我来回答问题。最初的问题是，
why did people transition into agriculture?
为什么人们会转向农业？
And the theory that most scholars believe is because of religion.
而大多数学者认为的理论是因为宗教。
It was because people had a religious need
因为人们有宗教需求。
that they came together to have these religious festivals.
他们聚在一起，举行这些宗教节日。
There were some charismatic leaders who were
有些有魅力的领袖，十分出众，大家便跟随他们定居。
so brilliant that people chose to settle down with them.
Okay? And so, they became sanitary.
好的？于是他们变得干净。
They developed a religion around the sanitary lifestyle,
他们围绕清洁生活方式发展了一种宗教，包括祖先崇拜。
which included ancestor worship.
But over time, because
但随着时间的推移，因为你停留在同一处，你会耗尽周边资源。
you're in one place, you're going to deplete the resources of the area around you,
于是你会把宗教带到新地方。
right? Of the forest. Which means that you must go to farming.
对吧？来自森林的那点意思是你必须去耕种。
Okay? Does that make sense? So,
好吧？这样说通吗？
but then eventually, because you have so much population
但随后，随着人口的增加
and you farm too much, you're forced to move somewhere else.
以及耕种的扩张，你被迫迁移到别处
And when you move somewhere else, you actually bring your religion with you.
当你迁移到别处时，你会把宗教带过去。
Okay? And that's how we can explain the culture.
好吧？这就是我们解释文化的方式。
And that's how we can explain the transition from hunter -gatherer to agriculture.
于是我们就能解释从狩猎采集到农业的转变。
And there was no one spark or one moment when this happened.
并且没有哪一瞬间或哪一火花促成此变。
We think it took thousands of years over time.
我们认为这需要数千年的时间。
Because ultimately,
因为最终，
the hunter -gatherer lifestyle was
狩猎采集的生活方式是
so much more attractive to people, so much easier
如此更吸引人，且更容易
and attractive to people than the farming lifestyle.
比农耕生活更吸引人
Okay? But the benefit of the farming lifestyle is that you had a religion.
好的？但农耕生活的好处在于它让你拥有宗教。
And that's why people chose ultimately to farm.
这就是人们最终选择农耕的原因。
Okay? So that's it.
好了，就是这样。
And next class, we'll continue this discussion about early religion.
接下来一节课，我们继续讨论早期宗教。
And how people developed these religious visions.
以及人们如何形成这些宗教观念。
Okay? So next class, we'll look at ice cave paintings
好了，下一节课我们来看看冰洞壁画。
that goes back 40,000 years.
回溯四万年前。
Meaning that they practiced this sort of religion or something like this religion 40 to 50,000 years ago.
也就是说他们在四万五千年前有类似这种宗教的实践。
And we know through ice cave paintings.
我们通过冰洞壁画知道这一点。
Okay. So
好的。那就
questions before we finish class.
在结束课堂之前还有问题吗？
Is this clear to you guys?
这对你们来说清楚吗？
Okay? Anything you're confused about?
好的？你有什么不懂的吗？
Any questions before we conclude?
在结束之前还有问题吗？
Okay. Do you see it more clearly?
好的。你看得更清楚了吗？
And again, this is all on the internet, by the way.
再说一次，这些都在网上，顺便说一句。
So if you're interested, you can go online and just read up more on Catahoyac.
如果你感兴趣，可以上网再多读点关于Catahoyac的资料。
Okay? These places are very famous.
好的？这些地方非常有名气。
We'll be discussing these places throughout the semester.
我们将在整个学期讨论这些地方。
Okay? Cabo Batepe, Jericho, and Catahoyac.
好吧？Cabo Batepe、Jericho 和 Catahoyac。
Excuse me?.
请问一下。
. We discussed all three.
我们已经讨论过这三处。
Okay? But I'm introducing you to these three places.
好的？但我先把这三处介绍给你们。
In future classes, we'll go more in depth into these places.
在后续课程里，我们会更深入地探讨这些地方。
Okay? Because Cabo Batepe is a very interesting place.
好的？因为Cabo Batepe是一个非常有趣的地方。
Okay? And
好的？而且
we're only slowly discovering all that's there.
我们只是在慢慢发现那里的全部内容。
Basically, we basically uncovered about 5% of Cabo Batepe.
基本上，我们已经发掘了Cabo Batepe的约5%。
So over the next few decades, we'll know more.
接下来几十年，我们会了解更多。
Okay? Any more questions?
好？还有问题吗？
Any more questions? Okay.
还有问题吗？好的。
All right. So next class, we will do Ice Cave paintings. .
好的。下节课我们来做冰洞壁画。